Guide to the German Correspondence from the World Wars Collection 1916-1946 MSS 161 MSS.161
Fales Library and Special Collections
German Correspondence from the World Wars Collection
1916 - 1946
Fales Library and Special Collections
Apfelbaum, Charles
MSS.161
6 Linear Feet (17 boxes)
German Correspondence from the World Wars contains letters to/from German soldiers and their friends and family. Only one set of correspondence, that of soldier Hermann Lappan, is from the First World War. The collection also contains two diaries of a German soldier involved in the Balkan Campaign, miscellaneous soldiers' documents, as well as correspondence (in English) between a young Italian soldier and a young American student.
Provenance
The collection was purchased from Charles Apfelbaum Rare Manuscripts and Archives in 2003.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Historical Note
We lay aside letters never to read them again, and at last we destroy them out of discretion, and so disappears the most beautiful, the most immediate breath of life, irrecoverable for ourselves and for others.
-Johann Wolfgang von Goethe
The estimated death toll of the Second World War (1937-1945), perhaps the most extensively studied event in the twentieth century, is between 50 and 56 million people. This includes democides, military and civilian casualties, and those missing in action throughout all of the war's various theatres. It may seem difficult to imagine "life" in such a deadly and uncertain time, and yet, as these letters mainly written by German Wehrmacht soldiers and their families demonstrate, the everyday, or a nostalgia for it, persisted. Here, a soldier's letter back to his parents might complain about a small ration of sausage, and how his mother's cooking is missed, only to be followed by a letter that details an injury sustained on the front. The "immediate" quality of the letters obviously cannot always be taken at face value. A soldier, aware of the severity of censors, was probably not able to write as freely as he wished. The letters often do not contain as detailed information of military activities as some researchers might wish. Apart from the generally strong sense of Heimat, political attitudes and statements about the government, especially critical ones that could lead to the death penalty, are infrequently broached directly. Yet, this collection reveals, sometimes strinkingly, the often missing "human" aspect of a seemingly very inhumane time and place - National Socialist Germany. These Feldpostbriefe[letters from/to the front], though an infinitesmal representation of the 40-50 billion sent and received in Germany throughout WWII, will prove interesting to researchers interested in the Axis from "the bottom up" and in German war correspondence in general. A short bibliography on Feldpostbriefe and the German soldier, which may assist the researcher, follows.
Fritz, Stephen G. Frontsoldaten: the German soldier in World War II. Lexington, Ky: University Press of Kentucky, 1995.
Buchbender, Ortwin, and Reinhold Sterz, eds. Das andere Gesicht des Krieges: Deutsche Feldpostbriefe, 1939-1945. Munich: Beck, 1982.
Golovchanski, Anatoly. "Ich will raus aus diesem Wahnsinn": deutsche Briefe von der Ostfront 1941-1945: aus sowjetischen Archiven. Wuppertal: P. Hammer; [Moskow]: Verlagsvereinigung des Schriftstellerverbandes der UdSSR, 1991.
Knoch, Peter. "Feldpost - eine unentdeckte historische Quellengattung." Geschichtsdidaktik 11, no. 2 (1986): 154-71.
Knoch, Peter, ed. Kriegsalltag: Die Rekonstruktion des Kreigsalltags als Aufgabe der historischen Forschung und der Friedenserziehung. Stuttgart: Metzler, 1989.
Kretschmer, Volker, and Detlef Vogel. "Feldpostbriefe im Zweiten Weltkrieg: Propagandainstrument und Spiegelbild von Kriegsauswirkungen. Sozialwissenschaftliche Informationen 2 (1990): 103-10.
Lakowski, Richard, and Hans-Joachim Büll. Lebenszeichen 1945: Feldpost aus den letzten Kriegstagen. Leipzig: Militzke, 2002.
Wette, Wolfram, ed. Der Krieg des Kleinen Mannes: Eine Militärgeschichte von unten. Munich, Piper, 1992.
Scope and Content Note
The majority of German Correspondence from the World Wars consists of letters to and from German soldiers and their families. The correspondence varies from a brief New Year's postcard to a long letter from the front. There is also correspondence (the only in English) and related ephemera mailed between a young American student, Shirley Messinger, and a young Italian soldier. There are two small diaries, which include details of the German campaign in the Balkans, of WWII soldier Engelhard Hellmuth. The collection also contains two Soldbuecher (military identification cards), certificates of honor (e.g., Ehrenkreuz für Frontkämpfer), as well as some photographs and newspaper clippings accompanying individual pieces of correspondence.
SERIES DESCRIPTION
SERIES I: Lappan, Hermann
The majority of these letters are from Hermann Lappan to his family. This is the one series in the collection that dates from World War I.
SERIES II: Berger, Wolfgang
The majority of these letters are to and from Wolfgang and Richard Berger and their family.
SERIES III: Hellmuth, Engelhard
Series III contains two diaries of Engelhard Hellmuth, who, in 1942, was a Hauptscharführer [Head Company Leader] (the equivalent of the Wermacht rank of Oberfeldwebel, which is roughly equivalent to the American Master Sergeant) with the S.S., or Schutzstaffel [Protection Unit]. During this time, Hellmuth was involved in the German campaign in the Balkans.
SERIES IV: Jensen, Kurt
Series IV is entirely comprised of letters from Jensen back home to his parents in Schleswig, a city that is between Hamburg and Denmark, closer to the latter. From late January of 1942 to February of 1943, Jensen was on the Russian front. His last letter (April 1, 1945) bears the postmark of Wittenberge, which was bombed by the American Ninth Air Force on April 10 and 12.
SERIES V: Riedel, Helmut
The majority of the letters in this series are to Helmut Riedel, who was an Obergefreiter [Corporal] in World War II. There are also a number of letters addresed to Matrose [Sailor] Riedel. Most letters are from family and freinds in Chemnitz. There are some letters, usually sans envelope, penned by Helmut. There is a large number of letters without a corresponding envelope.
SERIES VI: Schiavi, Pietro, and Shirley Messinger
Series VI contains the letters of a young Italian, Pietro Schiavi, to his Rhode Island penpal, Shirley Messinger. The correspondence of this series is in English, not German. The letters, which date from April 1935 to January 1945, trace Schiavi's trajectory from student to soldier to prisoner of war in Germany. Schivai signs his name first as Pietro, then as Pete and Piero; he also begins to refer to Shirley as Wally. The series contains the various "gifts" that Schiavi sent - a pressed flower, photos, newspaper clippings, and a postcard book. The series also contains memorabilia from Messinger's high school and college (Pembroke) years and a manuscript, "Facts about Pietro Schiavi," which includes an inventory of "Letters Received."
SERIES VII: Eugen Uhl; Josef (Sepp) Jung
Subseries A: Uhl, Eugen
Series VII, Sub-series A contains roughly 450 pieces of correspondence dating from 1936 to 1946, with the majority of the letters dating from 1942 to 1944. The letters center around Eugen and Waldemar Uhl, both of whom were in the German army, and their parents in St. Ingbert (Saar), Ernst and Therese Uhl. Waldemar's last letter home is from June 23, 1941. The letters from Ernst and Therese begin in late 1942; almost all are addressed to Eugen. It appears that Ernst Uhl successfully petitioned for his son Eugen's removal from the front to "[a less dangerous post]" in March of 1943 (see Atbacher, March 18, 1943, and Hauptmann [...], March 22, 1943). The majority of letters in this subseries are between Eugen and his parents.
Subseries B: Jung, Josef
Interspersed with the Uhl family letters were about 35 letters addressed to Obergefreiter [Corporal] Josef (or Sepp, with the familiar form Seppel, which can be abbreviated as Sepp'l) Jung. No immediate relationship between Jung and Uhl is apparent.
SERIES VIII: Werle, Jakob
The majority of the letters in this series are to Jakob Werle. The remaining letters are addressed either to the Werle Family or sent by Jakob himself. The reader will notice that Werle's hand is radically different in the letter of February 14, 1944 from the military hospital at Wenden due to his injuries from a grenade explosion in Russia. From the German hospital in Wenden, Werle was transferred to a military hospital in Choroszcz, near Bialystok, in Poland. From Poland, he was moved back to Germany, to the hospital at Erfurt, from where his last letter, the latest dated (February 15, 1945) letter in this series, was sent.
SERIES IX: Zieher, Gottlob
With the exception of a single letter, dated February 18, 1943, Gottlob Zieher's correspondence is comprised of letters received. The majority of these are letters from Zieher's siblings, many from Frieda Zieher, who wrote from the family's hometown, Dinkelsbühl. The last letter sent to Zieher, from his sister Lina, is dated August 20, 1944.
SERIES X: Miscellaneous wartime documents
Series X contains miscellaneous items that, at the time of acquisition, were, seemingly arbitrarily, grouped with the correspondence of Gottlob Zieher. These items, labelled as miscellaneous documents, include soldier identification books, certificates of military honor, and an application to the Evangelical church, among others.
Oversize
All three items placed in oversize are from Series VI: Schiavi and Messinger.
Arrangement
At the series level, the correspondence is arranged first by its larger historical context (i.e., first World War I, here represented solely by the Lappan correspondence, and then World War II), and then alphabetically by the last name of the soldier by/to whom the correspondence is written.
At the folder level, correspondence is arranged alphabetically by last name of the writer. When a writer's name is either not present or not at all legible, that writer's correspondence is presented at the end of the series. Each writer's correspondence is presented chronologically in his/her respective folder(s). When an item's date is either not present or not legible, that item is presented at the end of the writer's folder(s).
Series X contains miscellaneous items that, at the time of acquisition, were, seemingly arbitrarily, grouped with the correspondence of Gottlob Zieher. These items, labelled as miscellaneous documents, include soldier identification books, certificates of military honor, and an application to the Evangelical church, among others.
Missing Title
Series I: Hermann Lappan
Series II: Wolfgang Berger
Series III: Engelhard Hellmuth
Series IV: Kurt Jensen
Series V: Helmut Riedel
Series VI: Pietro Schiavi and Shirley Messinger
Series VII: Eugen Uhl and Josef (Sepp) Jung
Series VIII: Jakob Werle
Series IX: Gottlob Zieher
Series X: Miscellaneous Wartime Documents
Oversize - Series VI: Pietro Schiavi and Shirley Messinger
Related Material at Fales Library and Special Collections
The Erich Maria Remarque Papers
Separated Material
There is no record of materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Correspondence.; Identity cards.; Italy; Magazines (Periodicals); Soldiers |z Germany |v Correspondence.; Mussolini, Benito |d 1883-1945 |x Public opinion.; Choroszcz (Poland); Erufrt (Germany); Berlin (Germany); Chemnitz.; Dinkelsbühl (Germany); Germany.; Clippings (information artifacts); Munich (Germany); Poland; Providence (R.I.); Russia.; Schleswig (Germany); Decorations (honor); Vienna (Austria); Austria.; St. Ingbert (Germany); World War, 1939-1945 |x Postal service.; World War, 1939-1945 -- United States -- Public opinion.; World War, 1939-1945 |z Germany |x Public opinion.; World War, 1939-1945 |z Italy.; World War, 1914-1918 |z Germany.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Germany.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Correspondence.; Photographs.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Correspondence.; Soldiers |z Italy |v Correspondence.; Soldiers |z Germany |x History |y 20th century.
- Series I: Hermann Lappan
  Scope and Contents note
  The majority of these letters are from Hermann Lappan to his family. This is the one series in the collection that dates from World War I.
  - Dabow, Hermann- December 24, 1916- April 1, 1917, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dabow, Hermann- June 3, 1917- October 11, 1918, 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ehrenburg, Gottlieb- February 15, 1917- June 4, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Grossmit- November 11, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - [Hanow], Erich- January 24, 1917- July 6, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Kaiger, Ferdinand- September 10, 1918- December 6, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Klauck, H- February 12, 1917- August 8, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Krause, [Artur]- March 29, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Lappan, Hermann- August 4, 1914- March 18, 1916, 1914-1916 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Lappan, Hermann- March 20, 1916- April 21, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lappan, Hermann- April 26, 1916- May 3, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Lappan, Hermann- May 21, 1916- June 14, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Lappan, Hermann- July 8, 1916- July 26, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Lappan, Hermann- July 25, 1916- August 6, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Lappan, Hermann- August 12, 1916- September 14, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Lappan, Hermann- September 21, 1916- October 5, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Lappan, Hermann- October 6, 1916- November 16, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Lappan, Hermann- November 18, 1916- December 17, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Lappan, Hermann- December 17, 1916- February 11, 1917, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Lappan, Hermann- May 8, 1917- September 26, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Lappan, Hermann- October 19, 1917- November 1, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Lappan, Hermann- November 3, 1917- November 15, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Lappan, Hermann- November 22, 1917- January 13, 1918, 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Lappan, Hermann- January 29, 1918- March 17, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Lappan, Hermann- April 20, 1918- May 13, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Lappan, Hermann- May 24, 1918- June 21, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Lappan, Hermann- July 2, 1918- August 7, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Lappan, Hermann- August 11, 1918- January 21, 1919, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Lappan, Hermann- Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Lappan, Wilhelm- October 8, 1918- October 20, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Loh, Hermann Johann- March 3, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Muller, Heinz- April 15, 1917- June 23, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Passig, Felix- May 31, 1918- November 24, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Roggaty, Fritz- November 12, 1916- March 9, 1917, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Schmidt, Martin- June 16, 1917- August 9, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Urban, Gottfried- March 21, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Miscellaneous, Unidentified- October 27, 1916- December 6, 1917, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Series II: Wolfgang Berger
  The majority of these letters are to and from Wolfgang and Richard Berger and their family.
  - Balthaus, Marta- April 9, 1940- September 16, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Balthaus, Willi- April 10, 1940- July 26, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Balthaus, Willi- August 22, 1940- December 1, 1946, 1940-1946 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Berger, Friderike (Mutter)- October 15, 1934- April 26, 1938, 1934-1938 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Berger, Friderike (Mutter)- January 1, 1940- February 11, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Berger, Friderike (Mutter)- March 23, 1940- July 1, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Berger, Friderike (Mutter)- July 13, 1940- October 7, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Berger, Friderike (Mutter)- October 13, 1940- December 26, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Berger, Friderike (Mutter)- March 8, 1941- March 28, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Berger, Friderike (Mutter)- May 15, 1941- June 23, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Berger, Friderike (Mutter)- July 11, 1941- August 30, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Berger, Friderike (Mutter)- September 15, 1941- November 24, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Berger, Friderike (Mutter)- February 4, 1942- February 23, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Berger, Friderike (Mutter)- March 2, 1942- April 7, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Berger, Friderike (Mutter)-April 13, 1942- January 8, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Berger, Richard- October 17, 1934- March 16, 1942, 1934-42 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Berger, Richard- June 20, 1942- June 28, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Berger, Richard- July 5, 1942- July 29, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Berger, Richard- August 10, 1942- August 22, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Berger, Richard- August 26, 1942- September 27, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Berger, Richard- October 1, 1942- October 16, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Berger, Richard- October 22, 1942- December 8, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Berger, Richard- December 13, 1942- December 29, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Berger, Richard- January 22, 1943- February 7, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Berger, Richard- February 28, 1943- March 15, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Berger, Richard- March 18, 1943- April 4, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Berger, Richard- April 6, 1943- May 16, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- January 25, 1935- April 10, 1940, 1935-1940 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- April 18, 1940- June 30, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- July 5, 1940- August 2, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- August 7, 1940- September 8, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- September 15, 1940- October 10, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- October 12, 1940- December 15, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- January 1, 1941- January 26, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- January 30, 1941- February 6, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- February 8, 1941- March 3, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- March 8, 1941- March 30, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- April 5, 1941- April 27, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Berger, Wolfgang= May 5, 1941- May 19, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- May 23, 1941- May 31, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- June 15, 1941- October 5, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- October 19, 1941- November 19, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- November 27, 1941- December 15, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- December 21, 1941- December 31, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- January 4, 1942- February 12, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- February 16, 1942- March 17, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- April 11, 1942- May 8, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- May 13, 1942- June 6, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- July 6, 1942- July 22, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- July 26, 1942- July 29, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- August 6, 1942- August 17, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- August 18, 1942- September 4, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- September 11, 1942- September 30, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- October 8, 1942- October 17, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- October 23, 1942- December 17, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- December 20, 1942- February 28, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- March 3, 1943- March 17, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- April 1, 1943- May 8, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Berger, Wolfgang- undated (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Diercks, Arnold- July 16, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Finger, [ ]- September 27, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Fromme, Fran- September 23, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Haack, Heinz- January 27, 1940- February 15, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Heath, Richard- June 26, 1940- June 29, 1942, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - Hennings, Carl H.- June 2, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - [ ], Hildegard- April 8, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - Hinz, Robert- January 27, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - [Hoar], Theo- September 22, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - [Hoffmann]- July 30, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 106)
  - Jomacek- May 2, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - Kimm, Fritz- September 24, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 108)
  - [Kloar], Fritz and Gretel- August 29, 1936-September 1, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 109)
  - Loewe, Ernst- September 22, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 110)
  - Steen, Ernst- March 7, 1941- December 3, 1944, 1941-1944 (Box 3, Folder 111)
  - Volz, Annalisa- October 21, 1942- May 1, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 112)
  - Volz, Annalisa- undated (Box 3, Folder 112a)
  - Volz, Friedalore- June 13, 1940- May 2, 1943, 1940-1943 (Box 3, Folder 113)
  - Volz, Friedalore- undated (Box 3, Folder 113a)
  - Volz, Hans- May 8, 1943- May 11, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 114)
  - Weist, Adolf- December 18, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 115)
  - Willi and Lotti- December 19, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 116)
  - Unidentified- 1916-1951 (Box 3, Folder 117)
  - Unidentified- undated (Box 3, Folder 118)
  - Envelopes- 1938-1941 (Box 3, Folder 119)
- Series III: Engelhard Hellmuth
  Series III contains two diaries of Engelhard Hellmuth, who, in 1942, was a Hauptscharführer [Head Company Leader] (the equivalent of the Wermacht rank of Oberfeldwebel, which is roughly equivalent to the American Master Sergeant) with the S.S., or Schutzstaffel [Protection Unit]. During this time, Hellmuth was involved in the German campaign in the Balkans.
  - Diary of Engelhard Hellmuth about the "Balkanfeldzug"- Jan 12, 1941- June 5, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 120)
  - Diary of Engelard Hellmuth- March 17, 1942- May 10, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 121)
- Series IV: Kurt Jensen
  Series IV is entirely comprised of letters from Jensen back home to his parents in Schleswig, a city that is between Hamburg and Denmark, closer to the latter. From late January of 1942 to February of 1943, Jensen was on the Russian front. His last letter (April 1, 1945) bears the postmark of Wittenberge, which was bombed by the American Ninth Air Force on April 10 and 12.
  - Jensen, Kurt- November 23, 1941- April 6, 1942, 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 122)
  - Jensen, Kurt- April 23, 1942- July 19, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 123)
  - Jensen, Kurt- July 20, 1942- September 10, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 124)
  - Jensen, Kurt-September 10, 1942- December 16, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 125)
  - Jensen, Kurt- December 20, 1942- April 3, 1943, 1942-1943 (Box 4, Folder 126)
  - Jensen, Kurt- April 7, 1943- May 27, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 127)
  - Jensen, Kurt- May 31, 1943- August 1, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 128)
  - Jensen, Kurt- August 8, 1943- September 4, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 129)
  - Jensen, Kurt- September 6, 1943- December 20, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 130)
  - Jensen, Kurt- December 14, 1943- March 25, 1944, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 131)
  - Jensen, Kurt- April 3, 1944- June 15, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 132)
  - Jensen, Kurt- June 16, 1944- August 29, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 133)
  - Jensen, Kurt- August 27, 1944- October 13, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 134)
  - Jensen, Kurt- October 18, 1944-November 26, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 135)
  - Jensen, Kurt- November 29, 1944- March 1, 1945, 1944-1945 (Box 4, Folder 136)
  - Jensen, Kurt- March 17, 1945- April 1, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 137)
  - Jensen, Kurt- undated (Box 4, Folder 137a)
- Series V: Helmut Riedel
  The majority of the letters in this series are to Helmut Riedel, who was an Obergefreiter [Corporal] in World War II. There are also a number of letters addresed to Matrose [Sailor] Riedel. Most letters are from family and freinds in Chemnitz. There are some letters, usually sans envelope, penned by Helmut. There is a large number of letters without a corresponding envelope.